Guide to the Stanley Yale Beach Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stanley Yale Beach papers
1911-1948
1917-1933
GEN MSS 802
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.42
(14 boxes)
The papers primarily contain correspondence between Stanley Yale Beach and his family, friends, and colleagues in the aeronautical and engineering fields. The bulk of the collection is his correspondence with engineers and manufacturers, in particular those in Germany, as well as with his friend, poet Harry Arthur Powell. A small group of files reveal Beach's investigation into the missing French aviators Charles Nungesser and François Coli, and his relationship with the New York clairvoyant Mrs. Almira Gaylord Beach, who practiced as Vesta la Viesta. Family correspondence largely deals with Beach's chaotic personal life and finances, and a group of legal and financial files serve as well to document that aspect of his life. Also present is a group of early aviation and engineering photographs, some including American Brigadier General William Mitchell, and ephemera related to Beach's personal and professional interests.
Beach, Stanley Yale
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company (Swann Galleries sale, 2010 March 18, lot 43) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Stanley Yale Beach (1877-1955)
Stanley Yale Beach, an American inventor, descended from a prominent family of noted inventors, engineers, and publishers in New York and Connecticut. His great-grandfather was Moses Yale Beach (1800-1868), an inventor, publisher of the New York Sun, and founder of the Associated Press. His grandfather was Alfred Ely Beach (1826-1896), for fifty years the editor and publisher of the journal Scientific American, though best remembered for two of his inventions, a Braille typewriter for the blind and the Beach Pneumatic Railway, the first subterranean transit system in New York City. His father was Frederick Converse Beach (1848-1918), an 1868 graduate of the Sheffield Scientific School of Yale University, a New York patent attorney, photographer, founding editor of the journal American Amateur Photographer, publisher and editor of Scientific American, and editor-in-chief of the Encyclopedia Americana.
Stanley Yale Beach was born on July 9, 1877, in Stratford, Connecticut, to Frederick and Margaret Gilbert Beach. Like his father, he attended the Sheffield Scientific School, graduating in 1898, and afterward developed a lifetime interest in aeronautics, engineering, and inventing. In 1897 Beach eloped with Helen Birdseye Curtis, a student at Wellesley College and a resident of Stratford, where the couple settled and raised their children Frederick, Alfred, and Margaret. Even though he had a career as first "Automobile Editor" and then "Aeronautic Editor" of Scientific American, Beach appears to have been primarily supported by income from a trust set up by his father in 1914, and by checks received periodically from his mother. During the week Beach operated out of the Beach Building at 125 East 23rd Street in New York City, and from there ran various entrepreneurial enterprises such as the Beach Engineering Company, the Beach Laboratories, the Scientific Aeroplane Company, and associations including the Aero Science Club. Also during the week and in New York, Beach maintained an apartment and a secret second family: his paramour Marie Danner, also known as Caroline Watson, and their daughter Winifred, also known as Marguerite. Helen Beach was aware of her husband's infidelity from Winifred's birth in 1908, but refused his request to grant him a divorce so that he might marry Marie and allow Winifred to be legally recognized in the Beach family inheritance his other children would receive. His wife, sister, son, and other family members collaborated to suspend Beach's trust payments when the affair became public in 1925, and when Beach subsequently took them to court, the proceedings were covered in the New York newspapers with headlines such as "Stirs Skeleton of Blue Bloods." Stanley and Helen Beach were divorced in 1928 and he married Marie Danner on June 14 of that year.
Although he fell out with most of the members of his family over his finances and life choices, Beach maintained a good relationship with his wealthy aunt, Jennie Beach Gasper, who was one of his trustees. He was also a favorite of his grandmother, Harriet Holbrook Beach, who had developed a great interest in Spiritualism. Within a year of her husband Alfred's death Harriet Beach married a medium, Henry Richardson Rogers, in Alexandria, Egypt, and soon after her two children, upon finding that their mother had signed their late father's significant fortune over to Rogers, began legal proceedings to declare her mentally incompetent; they succeeded, and the marriage was annulled in May 1899. A quarter-century later, Stanley Yale Beach also took an interest in Spiritualism and formed a friendship with the blind New York clairvoyant Vesta la Viesta, known for her detailed public presentations on her journeys to Mars and Venus. He appears to have worked as a secretary to her, and used the verso of her letterhead to make carbon copies of his outgoing correspondence.
Stanley Yale Beach died in New City, New York, on July 13, 1955.
Beach Family Tree
Principal correspondents are underlined.
Moses Yale Beach (1800-1868) m. Nancy Day
- -1 Alfred Ely Beach (1826-1896) m. 1847 Harriet Eliza Holbrook (1828-1905)
- -- -- 2 Frederick Converse Beach (1848-1918) m. 1875 Margaret Allen Gilbert (1848-1932)
- -- -- -- 3 Stanley Yale Beach (1877-1955) m. 1897-1928 Helen Birdseye Curtis (1878-1947)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Frederick Converse Beach (1898-1940) m. 1934 Matilda Florence Sparling (1911-1941)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Alfred Birdseye Beach (1899-1985) m. ca. 1929 Alice Elizabeth Perkins (1901-1978)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Margaret Stanley Beach (1901-1983) m. 1933 Elwyn Moore Deakins (1905-1986)
- -- -- -- - m. 2nd 1928 Marie Danner [also known as Caroline Watson] (1888-1961)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Winifred [also known as Marguerite] (1908-2002) m. 1933 Leonard Martin
- -- -- -- 3 Alfred Gilbert Beach (1879-1890)
- -- -- -- 3 Ethel Holbrook Beach (1886-1937) m. 1909 James Albert Wales (1879-1970)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 James A. Wales Jr. (1913-1985)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Richard B. Wales (1917-2009)
- -- -- -- -- - 4 Nancy Holbrook Wales (b. 1927) m. 1947 Gordon Douglas Swaffield (1919-2003)
- -- --2 Jennie Holbrook Beach [called "Tante"] (1850-1932) m. 1896 Marquis Cossitt Gasper (d. 1908)
Scope and Contents
The papers primarily contain correspondence between Stanley Yale Beach and his family, friends, and colleagues in the aeronautical and engineering fields. The bulk of the collection is his correspondence with engineers and manufacturers, in particular those in Germany, as well as with his friend the poet Harry Arthur Powell. A small group of files reveal Beach's investigation into the missing French aviators Charles Nungesser and François Coli. Family correspondence largely deals with Beach's chaotic personal life and finances, and a group of legal and financial files serve as well to document that aspect of his life. Also present is a group of early aviation and engineering photographs, and ephemera related to Beach's personal and professional interests.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. General Correspondence and Photographs, 1911-1948. II. Family Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1915-1933. III. Other Papers, 1924-1935.
Aeronautical engineers -- Germany; Aeronautical engineers -- United States; Aeronautics -- Germany; Aeronautics -- United States; Airplanes -- Germany; Airplanes -- United States; Airships -- United States; Clairvoyance -- United States; Clairvoyants -- United States; Inventors -- United States; Psychic ability -- United States; Psychic readings -- United States; Photographs -- Germany -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Aeronautical engineers -- United States -- 20th Century; Clairvoyants -- United States -- 20th Century; Inventors -- United States -- 20th Century; Basenach, Nikolaus; Beach, Almira Gaylord; Beach, Frederick Converse, 1898-1941; Beach, Margaret Gilbert, 1848-1932; Beach, Stanley Yale; Coli, François, 1881-1927; Gasper, Jennie Holbrook, -1932; Gregory, Elizabeth Hiatt, 1872-1955; Meyer, C. W. Erich; Mitchell, William, 1879-1936; Nungesser, Charles, 1892-1927; Polglase, Julyan; Powell, H. Arthur (Harry Arthur), 1877-; Schoop, M. U.; Stevens, A. Leo (Albert Leo), 1877-1944; Vincent, Ernest Peter; Wright, Frank C.; Aero Science Club; Beach Engineering Company
- General Correspondence and Photographs, 1911-1948; Series I; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Photographs.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence with Beach's friends and professional colleagues, including engineers, aviators, manufacturers, and others working in aeronautical and mechanical pursuits. Several files hold both sides of the correspondence, as Beach kept carbon copies of many of his outgoing letters, typed or handwritten. In addition to research for his own projects, he was often trying to interest potential investors in his ideas and inventions, and topics covered in the letters include television systems, astrology, patents, patent attorneys, inventors, oil exploration, and aeronautical fabrics. Prominent among the correspondents are the German engineers Nikolaus Basenach, C. W. Erich Meyer, and Max U. Schoop; manufacturers such as the Centrifugal Hammer Company; aviators such as Frank C. Wright (François Raiche); and inventors including Henry House and Ernest Peter Vincent. One of the largest sets of correspondence is with Harry Arthur Powell, a friend and poet who had worked for a time for Scientific American. Also in the series is his correspondence with the psychic Mrs. Almira Gaylord Beach (familial relationship to Stanley Beach unknown) who practiced under the name Vesta la Viesta, and some correspondence she had received from others. Beach appears to have worked for her, as well as having consulted her for his investigation of the fate of the French aviators Charles Nungesser and François Coli, whose biplane, the White Bird, disappeared in 1927 while attempting the first non-stop transatlantic flight between Paris and New York. Also present is Beach's correspondence with M. A. Thoms of Toronto, J. T. Richards at the Anglican Mission of Flower's Cove, Newfoundland, and John Stone, a local resident who heard the White Bird pass overhead. In a single letter to Howard Hughes, Beach asks for an appointment to present his plans for a dirigible for Hughes's use; his reply is not in the papers.
  Photographs follow the correspondence files; some may have once been enclosed in letters but were later separated, while others may have been collected or taken by Beach. The images are predominantly related to aeronautics and engineering, and had already been grouped by subject before the Beach papers arrived at the library. Among the photographs are a set related to a stunt flying event at the airfield in Mineola, on New York's Long Island; noted American Brigadier General William (Billy) Mitchell is among the participating aviators. Additional photographs appear in correspondence files in this series, in particular the folders for Basenach and Meyer which contain early aviation images, and Schoop, a pioneer developer of thermal spray devices for coating metals, whose letters included photographs of him and his tools.
  - Correspondence
    Folders of chronologically arranged general correspondence follow the alphabetically arranged files.
    - Adams, Evangeline, 1930 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aero Corporation of America, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aero Science Club, 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aircraft Development Corporation, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Airships Incorporated, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Altherr, John, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Institute of the City of New York, 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Atkinson, William Mayo, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Basenach, Nikolaus, 1925-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    - Beach, Almira Gaylord (Vesta la Viesta), 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Bureau for Scientific Investigation and Demonstration of Psychic Phenomena, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Centrifugal Hammer Company, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cohen, Ch. R., Miss, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cotton, Sidney, 1927 August 9 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Curtiss, Sadie, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Dey, Harry E., 1926 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Dickson, William Bradford, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Durant, Ed, 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fraprie, Frank Roy, 1932 -1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Gluck, M. B., 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Goldberg, Israel, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gregory, Elizabeth Hiatt, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Grey, C. G. (Charles Grey), 1924-1930 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Hart, M. M., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Harworth, Julius W., 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Heinen, Anton
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Aero Corporation of America
    - Heinkel, E., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hopkins, William Perry, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - House, Henry A., 1920-1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Hughes, Howard, 1930 Oct 2 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Jarosch, W. M., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Kettler, Fred, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Knight, William, 1927, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Lescarboura, Austin C. (Austin Celestin), 1924-1933 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Lewis, Henry E., 1924 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Martin, Robert P.
      See: Centrifugal Hammer Company
    - Meyer, C. W. Erich, 1922-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 38-41)
    - Miller and Miller, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Nydegger, James A., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - O'Brien, Eoghan, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Pelman Institute of America, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Petzoldt, Clara, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Pluecker, Max A. and Katherine D., 1919-1926 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Polglase, Julyan, 1919-1930 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Pollock, Leland Wells, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Postal Telegraph-Cable Company, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Powell, H. Arthur (Harry Arthur), 1924-1933 (Box 4, Folder 51-55)
    - Raiche, François
      See: Wright, Frank C.
    - Richards, J. T., 1927 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Rush, Ada L., 1930, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Schoop, Max Ulrich, 1927-1931 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Scientific American, 1912-1926 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Scott, Emma Louise, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Shadecki, William J., 1924-1927 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Slady, J. D., 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Stevens, A. Leo (Albert Leo), 1911-1931 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
    - Stone, John, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Thoms, M. A., 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Viesta, Vesta la
      Existence and Location of Originals
      See: Beach, Almira Gaylord
    - Vincent, Ernest Peter, 1927-1948 (Box 5, Folder 67-68)
    - Walter H. Baker Company, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Willis, F. Milton, 1925-1932 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Wright, Frank C., 1920-1933 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Zimmerman, James G., 1928-1931 (Box 6, Folder 72-73)
    - General correspondence, 1914-1927 (Box 6, Folder 74-77)
    - General correspondence, 1928-1933 (Box 7, Folder 78-81)
    - General correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Letter fragments, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 7, Folder 84-85)
  - Photographs
    - Dirigibles, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Model airplanes, undated (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Motors and engineering, undated (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Motor vehicles, undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Seaplanes, undated (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Stunt flying, Mineola, New York, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
      General note
      Includes photographs of Brigadier General William Mitchell
    - Family, undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
      Also contains unlabeled photographs of an elderly woman who may be Jennie Beach Gasper, Margaret Gilbert Beach, or possibly Almira Beach (Vesta la Viesta)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8, Folder 93)
- Family Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1915-1933; Series II; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Personal Papers.
  The series contains Beach's correspondence with his mother, aunt, children, cousins, and others, primarily related to the financial and legal issues with which Beach vexed his family over many years. Also present are folders of insurance and financial documents, the latter mostly related to his disputes with banks and firms to which he owed money for services rendered. Following those are legal files largely regarding the administration of Beach's trust account and his attempts to engage counsel to argue on his behalf against his family and various business firms.
  - Correspondence
    - Beach, Frederick Converse, 1919-1933 (Box 9, Folder 94-95)
      See also: Powell, H. Arthur (in Series I, box 4, folder 52)
    - Beach, Helen Birdseye Curtis, 1916-1925 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Beach, Hubert C., 1920-1931 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Beach, Margaret, 1914-1931 (Box 9, Folder 98-101)
    - Beach, Winifred, 1931-1933 (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Deakins, Margaret Beach, 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Gasper, Jennie Beach, 1915-1931 (Box 10, Folder 104-105)
    - Rider, Stanley Forbes, 1928-1933 (Box 10, Folder 106-107)
    - Wales, James Albert, and Ethel Holbrook Beach, 1919-1933 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Family, miscellaneous, 1923-1928 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Personal Papers
    - Financial papers, 1917-1933 (Box 11, Folder 110-113)
    - Insurance papers, 1924-1932 (Box 11, Folder 114-115)
    - Legal papers, 1914-1933, undated (Box 12, Folder 116-134)
- Other Papers, 1924-1935; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series III is arranged in alphabetical order.
  The series holds miscellaneous material, primarily ephemera, related to Beach's life and work. The clippings were cut from newspapers; some may have been enclosed in letters in Series I and II, but were later separated and grouped together before the collection arrived at the library. The topics are varied but many are stories and news reports on themes predominant in Beach's life: airplanes, divorces, and inheritances. Technology ephemera contains published brochures and trade catalogs for machines, air and motor vehicles, and other advances such as the Telegraphone; it also contains a copy of Beach's own brochure "To Make America the Birth Place of the Vertically Rising Aeroplane" with one of his business cards. Writings contains manuscripts, typescripts, and printed versions of writings by Beach. The final folders contain scraps of paper and other ephemera too varied for classification.
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1924-1933 (Box 13, Folder 135-137)
  - Psychic readings, diary notes, lists, undated (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Scientific American issues, 1933-1935 (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Technology ephemera, undated (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Theatre programs, 1927-1933 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - Writings, undated (Box 13, Folder 142-143)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera and papers, undated (Box 14, Folder 144-146)